Reinhold Niebuhr Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Addition III, 1907-1992 (Box 46-57)
  - Subject File, 1916-1992 (Box 54-56)
    Correspondence, clippings, and printed material.
    Arranged alphabetically by topic.
    - Adams, Larry L., 1978-1980, undated (Box 54)
    - American Friends of German Freedom, 1944, 1946
    - Articles and essays regarding Niebuhr and his work, 1937-1992, undated, (4 folders)
    - Augustine, undated
    - Baldwin, James, 1963-1964, 1982
    - Barth, Karl, 1929-1963, undated
    - Bethel Evangelical Church, Detroit, Mich., 1928, 1969-1972, undated (Box 55)
    - Biographical clippings, 1931-1991, undated, (4 folders)
    - Bonhoeffer, Dietrich, 1945, 1978-1988
    - Cathedral Church of St. John the Divine, New York, N.Y., 1973-1975, undated
    - Catholicism, 1965-1982, undated
    - Caustin, Bernard See Container 56, Niemöller, Martin
    - Coffin, Henry Sloane, retirement from Union Theological Seminary, New York, N.Y., 1945
    - Condolences on Niebuhr's death, 1971-1972
    - Cottage at Heath, Mass., 1979-1981, undated
    - Eddy, Sherwood, 1924, undated
    - Fox, Richard (Niebuhr biographer), 1979-1987, undated
    - Frankfurter, Felix, 1966-1968, 1977, undated
    - Groton School, Groton, Conn., seventy-fifth anniversary, undated (Box 56)
    - Herberg, Will, 1947-1977, undated
    - Interviews with Niebuhr, 1960-1969
    - Israel, 1937-1973, undated
    - Kester, Howard, 1935, 1990
    - Miscellany, 1934, 1951-1974, undated
    - Naudé, Beyers, 1970-1975, 1982-1985, undated
    - Niebuhr, H. Richard, 1962
    - Niebuhr, Ursula, 1969, 1972, 1978
    - Niebuhr, Walter, undated
    - Niemöller, Martin, 1942-1984, undated
    - Obituaries and memorials, 1971-1972, undated
    - Pauck, Wilhelm and Marion, 1976-1984, undated
    - Photographs, 1948, undated
    - Preachers, Billy Sunday and Billy Graham, 1916, circa 1980s
    - Researchers, 1972-1977
    - "Serenity" prayer, 1944-1987, undated
    - Student contemporaries, 1929, 1968-1970
    - Students and admirers, 1935, 1948-1986
    - Woodward, E. L. See also Container 53, same heading
      - Literary estate of, 1986-1987
      - Notes on Niebuhr's writings, [1958?]
      - Writings, 1946-1969
  - Writings, 1907-1986 (Box 56-57)
    Articles, addresses, reviews, and miscellaneous items.
    - Addresses, 1947, 1961 (Box 56)
    - Articles
      - Printed copies
        - 1918-1953, (2 folders)
        - 1954-1970, (3 folders) (Box 57)
      - Typescripts
        - "Detroit in the Twenties," undated
        - "The Detroit Microcosm in the American Industrial Macrocosm," circa 1960s
        - "Shoe Clerk a Woman Hater?" undated
        - "A View of Life From the Sidelines," 1967, 1984-1985
    - Bibliographies, 1925-1980, undated
    - Biographical statement, 1907
    - Lectures
      - Gifford lectures, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, Scotland, comments on, 1941-1942, 1954
      - "How Faith and Reason Are Related," 1950
    - Notes on ethics of social change, [1931?]
    - Reviews and comments
      - By Niebuhr, 1953-1970, undated
      - Of Niebuhr's books, 1929-1979, undated, (2 folders)
      - Of books regarding Niebuhr, 1956, 1960, 1986, undated
    - Sermon, "I Came That They May Have Life...," undated
- Addition IV, 1913-1994 (Box 58-67)
  - Family Correspondence, 1923-1971 (Box 58-60)
    Correspondence between Reinhold and Ursula Niebuhr and other family members.
    Arranged alphabetically by correspondent and chronologically thereunder.
    - Niebuhr, Reinhold (Box 58)
      - From
        - Niebuhr, H. Richard, 1930-1940, undated
      - To
        - Keppel-Compton, A. S. (Ursula Niebuhr's mother), 1932-1933
        - Niebuhr, Lydia (mother) and Hulda (sister), 1923, 1939, 1947-1948, undated
        - Niebuhr, Ursula
          - 1931-1937, (8 folders)
          - 1938-1970, undated, (16 folders) (Box 59)
    - Niebuhr, Ursula
      - To
        - Keppel-Compton, A. S. and J. H. (Ursula Niebuhr's parents), 1930-1933, undated, (4 folders)
        - Niebuhr, Reinhold, 1931-1970, (5 folders) (Box 60)
    - Various family members and friends, 1931-1971, undated
  - Professional File of Ursula Niebuhr, 1913-1994 (Box 60-67)
    Correspondence, articles, essays, lectures, speeches, sermons, notes, and administrative papers regarding her teaching career at Barnard College.
    Arranged alphabetically by type of material or topic and chronologically or alphabetically thereunder.
    - Barnard College, New York, N.Y. (Box 60)
      - Correspondence, 1955, undated
      - Courses
        - Introduction to the study of religion, 1963-1964, undated
        - Old and New Testaments, 1963-1964, undated
        - Religion, 1959-1964, undated (Box 61)
      - Former students, 1956-1981
      - Interfaith services, 1949-1956, undated
      - Office of Religious Affairs, 1951-1953
    - General correspondence
      - Amiran, David and Ruth, 1990-1994
      - Anderson, Carol, 1977-1991, undated
      - "A" miscellaneous, 1975-1991
      - Baillie, John, 1947
      - Barnes, John, 1991-1992
      - Barrett, Esmé, 1984-1992, undated
      - Barrette, Ray, 1985-1991, undated
      - Benn, Anthony ("Tony"), David, and June, 1959-1991, undated For additional material see Container 65, Margaret Stansgate
      - Berle, Adolf Augustus, Jr., and Beatrice, 1966-1984
      - Bossman, David M., 1981-1990
      - Brown, Charles C., 1990-1993
      - Brown, Robert McAfee, 1983-1991
      - Buoncristiano, Barbara, 1965-1991
      - Burlingham, Charles C., 1955-1958
      - "B" miscellaneous, 1942-1987, undated
      - Chartock, Roselle K., 1989
      - Cripps, Isobel, 1951-1959
      - "C" miscellaneous, 1953-1992, undated
      - "D" miscellaneous, 1948-1993
      - Ecumenical Institute for Advanced Theological Studies, Tantur, Israel, 1976-1982, undated (Box 62)
      - Emmet, Dorothy Mary, 1939-1991, undated
      - "E" miscellaneous, 1956-1994, undated
      - Fletcher, John C. and Dale, 1965-1990, undated
      - Franklin, Sam H., Jr., and Dorothy, 1987-1993
      - "F" miscellaneous, 1934-1993, undated, (2 folders)
      - Glauberman, Joan and George, 1972-1974, undated
      - "G" miscellaneous, 1931-1992, undated
      - Hall, Douglas John, 1990-1992, undated
      - Harlow, Gretta, 1948-1987
      - Harman, Avraham, 1969-1971
      - Harries, Richard, 1978-1993, undated
      - Havergal, Cynthia, 1945, 1972-1993, undated
      - Heschel, Abraham Joshua, re, 1968-1983, undated
      - Hussey, Margaret, 1941-1979
      - "H" miscellaneous, 1940-1992, undated (Box 63)
      - Israel, friends in, 1972-1987
      - "I" miscellaneous, 1933-1981, undated
      - Johnson, Sherman, 1972
      - Kennan, George F., 1971-1972
      - Kenyon, Kathleen, 1969-1973
      - Kilner, Bo (Mrs. John S.), 1965-1975, undated
      - Kollek, Teddy, 1971-1990, undated, (4 folders)
      - "K" miscellaneous, 1962-1992
      - Leith, John, 1970-1990, undated
      - Littell, Franklin H. and Marcia S., 1989-1990, undated
      - Lovett, Sidney and Joan, 1964-1993, undated
      - Lovitt, Harriet, 1952-1989, undated
      - Lynch, William F., 1950-1986, undated (Box 64)
      - "L" miscellaneous, 1959-1992, undated
      - MacLeish, Archibald, 1952-1956
      - Mailer, Norman, 1972-1976
      - Marty, Martin E., 1977-1992, undated
      - McGovern, George, 1967
      - McIntosh, Millicent, 1956-1990, undated
      - Mesinai, Susan Bromberg, 1964-1990
      - Miller, Charles, 1979-1991
      - Morgenthau, Hans J., 1970-1974
      - Mumford, Lewis and Sophia, 1973, 1989-1991
      - "M" miscellaneous, 1929-1992, undated, (2 folders)
      - "N" miscellaneous, 1930, 1965-1991, undated
      - "O" miscellaneous, 1969-1993, undated
      - Paton, Alan, concerning, 1992, undated
      - Pauck, Marion, 1977-1993, undated
      - Randall, John Herman, 1942, undated
      - Ranke-Heinemann, Uta, 1979, 1990-1991, undated
      - Roosevelt, Franklin D., III, 1966-1992, undated
      - "R" miscellaneous, 1930-1992, undated, (2 folders) (Box 65)
      - Sacks, Oliver W., 1993, undated
      - Schlesinger, Arthur M. (1917-2007), 1954-1972
      - Sedgwick, Ellery, 1931
      - Shriver, Donald W., 1978-1992, undated
      - Speers, Guthrie, 1969-1991, undated
      - Stansgate, Margaret, 1942-1991, undated, (2 folders)
      - Stewart, John B., 1954-1961, undated
      - "S" miscellaneous, 1951-1992, undated
      - Tickell, Reneé, 1974-1990, undated
      - "T" miscellaneous, 1965-1990, undated
      - Vidler, Alexander Roper, 1966-1991
      - Wyton, Alec, 1974-1990, undated
      - "W-Z" miscellaneous, 1959-1992, undated
      - Unidentified, 1958-1994
    - Miscellaneous clippings and printed matter, 1913-1977, undated (Box 66)
    - Speeches and writings
      - Articles and essays
        - "Christmas," 1947
        - "Every Woman's Right -- At Easter," 1948
        - "Faith, Hope and Love, These Three; But the Greatest of These Is Love," 1952
        - "Glory," 1983-1984
        - "The Gospel, Women, and the Church," 1951
        - "Historical Retrospect: English Friends and Influences," undated
        - "Holy Spirit," undated
        - "Is Dullness the Sin Against the Holy Spirit?" 1953
        - "Moral Wisdom," 1964
        - "Notes on a Friendship: Abraham Joshua Heschel and Reinhold Niebuhr," 1983
        - "Our Witness to the Resurrection," 1947
        - "Partakers of His Resurrection," 1953
        - "Show Me Thy Glory," undated
        - "Statesman or Politician," undated
        - "The Stuff and the Language of Religion," 1964, undated
        - "Two Days in Washington," 1979, undated
        - "Two English Bishops: William Temple," undated
        - "Union [Theological Seminary]: Then and Now, 1930 and 1955, Impressions and Recollections," 1955
        - "Women and the Church, and the Fact of Sex," 1951
        - "The World, the Flesh and the Devil," undated
      - Columns and other writings for the Berkshire Eagle, Pittsfield, Mass., 1972-1981, undated
      - Lectures
        - Borah Foundation Lectures, University of Idaho, Moscow, Idaho, 1954
        - McGill lecture, 1980
        - Sprunt lectures, Union Theological Seminary, Richmond, Va., 1977
      - Miscellaneous, 1947-1982, undated (Box 67)
      - Notes on
        - Church fathers and sex, undated
        - Ecclesia (the Church), undated
      - Prayers, 1956, undated
      - Sermon outlines, 1942-1944, 1959, 1967, undated, (2 folders)
      - Speeches, 1950, 1957-1977
      - Statements on Israel and Judaism, 1972-1979, undated
      - Typescripts of sound recordings of dialogues by Reinhold and Ursula Niebuhr
        - Christian belief, 1979, undated
        - Ford, Henry, and Detroit, Mich., undated
      - Working materials for Remembering Reinhold Niebuhr ([San Francisco]: HarperSanFrancisco, 1991), circa 1990
      - Worship services, 1950-1954, 1979, undated
- Addition V, 1990-1997 (Box 68-70)
  Correspondence, subject files, articles, essays, lectures, and reviews.
  Grouped by type of material and arranged alphabetically therein.
  - Correspondence (Box 68)
    - Amiran, David and Ruth, 1969, 1979-1988 See also Container 69, Jerusalem Committee, correspondence
    - “A” miscellaneous, 1989
    - Bingham, Jonathan and June, 1949-1952, 1959-1964, 1997, undated
    - “B-E” miscellaneous, 1925-1927, 1952, 1965-1971, 1987, 1993-1994
    - “F-J” miscellaneous, 1930-1931, 1947-1952, 1961-1970, 1979, 1989
    - Kollek, Teddy, 1969-1971, 1990-1997 See also Container 69, Jerusalem Committee, correspondence
    - “K-M” miscellaneous, 1925, 1954-1959, 1965, 1991-1996
    - Niebuhr family correspondence, 1910-1913, 1926, 1932, 1945, 1952, 1967-1968, 1978-1994, (2 folders)
    - Regarding Remembering Reinhold Niebuhr, [San Francisco]: Harper San Francisco, 1988-1992
    - Rockefeller Foundation, grant, 1957-1969
    - Roosevelt, Frank, 1965
    - Stone, Ronald H., 1965-1970
    - “S-W” miscellaneous, 1926-1931, 1951-1952, 1987-1997
    - Unidentified, 1940, 1957, 1991, 1997
  - Subject file
    - Awards and honors, 1942, 1948, 1954-1961, 1967-1969, 1992-1996
    - Bethel Evangelical Church, Detroit, Mich., 1924-1925, 1952, undated
    - Christian liturgy, 1972-1980
    - Clippings, 1922-1934, 1948-1979, 1992, undated
    - Fellowship of Socialist Christians, undated
    - Jerusalem Committee
      - Clippings, 1972-1989
      - Correspondence, 1970-1987 See also Container 68, Amiran, David and Ruth; and Kollek, Teddy, (3 folders) (Box 69)
      - Plenary sessions and conferences, 1969-1985
      - Printed matter, 1969-1985
    - Niebuhr, Christopher, 1949-1952, 1979
    - Obituaries and tributes, 1971-1972, 1992
    - Official documents, 1931-1932, 1952-1955, 1971, undated
    - Programs, 1938, 1949, 1983
    - Reinhold Niebuhr Award, 1971-1974
    - Serenity prayer, 1987-1993
  - Writings file
    - Lectures, notes, reports, 1935-1937, 1970-1971
    - Printed articles
      - By Niebuhr, Reinhold, 1916-1932, 1942-1971, (3 folders)
    - By Niebuhr, Ursula, 1954-1957, 1979 (Box 70)
    - By others, regarding Niebuhr and his work, 1944, 1954-1960, 1972- 1995, 2002, undated, (3 folders)
  - Reviews and comments
    - By Niebuhr, Reinhold, circa 1919, 1933-1945, 1955, 1965-1966
    - Of Niebuhr’s books, 1929, 1944
    - Of books regarding Niebuhr, 1948, 1956-1960, 1986, 1992-1995